Richard C. Carpenter Papers 2010.0105
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Richard C. Carpenter Papers
1889-2001.
2010.0105
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
33.0 Linear feet
Richard C. Carpenter is the author of A Railroad Atlas of the United States in 1946, a four volume set published by Johns Hopkins University Press. The papers include handdrawn original railroad track and signal maps drawn by Mr. Carpenter, Henry T. Wilhelm and William Bruce Coughlin, of railroads in the Mid-Atlantic States, New York and New England, and Indiana, Lower Michigan, and Ohio, that Mr. Carpenter used for research for the atlas.
33 linear feet.
Carpenter, Richard C.
Coughlin, William Bruce.
Wilhelm, Henry T., 1906-1994.
Biography
Richard Clark Carpenter was born on November 27, 1933, in Hartford, Connecticut. He was raised in Wethersfield, Connecticut, where he graduated from Wethersfield High School in 1951. He entered Boston College in 1951 and graduated in 1955 with a B.S. History degree. He joined the United States Army ROTC at Boston College and was commissioned a Second Lieutenant in the United States Army Artillery upon graduation. He served on active duty from 1955-1957 as platoon leader in the 66th Anti-Aircraft Missile Battalion (NiKE) as part of the defense of the New York Region. After starting a city planning career in Hartford, Connecticut, in 1958, he entered the University of Pennsylvania in 1960, graduating with a Master of City and Regional Planning degree in 1962.
After resuming his planning career in Hartford, Mr. Carpenter became the first town planner of Wilton, Connecticut, in 1963. He then became Executive Director of the South Western Regional Planning Agency in 1966, where he served until retiring in 1999.
Mr. Carpenter is currently a resident of East Norwalk, Connecticut. He married Mary Jane Campbell in 1958. They have two children, Ellin and John, and three grandchildren.
Mr. Carpenter is the author of the book series A Railroad Atlas of the United States in 1946, published by the Johns Hopkins University Press of Baltimore. To date, three volumes have been published: Volume 1 - The Mid-Atlantic States (2003), Volume 2 - New York and New England (2005), Volume 3 - Indiana, Ohio and Lower Michigan (2008), and Volume 4 - Illinois, Wisconsin and Upper Michigan. Volume 5 - Iowa and Minnesota - is currently in production by the author.
Little is known about the two men whose drawings are in the papers. Mr. Henry T. Wilhelm (1906-1994) was an electrical engineer for Bell Laboratories in New York City and then in Holmdel, New Jersey. Over his lifetime he apparently visited 2500 signal towers. Mr. William Bruce Coughlin was originally from Cincinnati, Ohio, and was a signal engineer with the General Railway Signalling Company in Rochester, New York.
General note
Published Works:
A Railroad Atlas of the United States in 1946, Johns Hopkins University Press.
Scope and Content
The Papers include drawings done by Henry T. Wilhelm, William Bruce Coughlin, and Richard C. Carpenter of main and branch line railroads and interlocking tower layouts, mainly in the United States and in particular in the regions that were represented in the first four volumes of Mr. Carpenter's work A Railroad Atlas of the United States in 1946. The materials created by Mr. Carpenter date from 1946 to 2001. The maps done by William Bruce Coughlin and Henry T. Wilhelm, were given to Mr. Carpenter by Mr. Wilhelm. These latter two collections contain similar drawings, dating from 1919 to the 1970s. A small number of the drawings were done by unknown others and were likely done as early as 1900.
The papers also includes official railroad track charts and signal department drawings of signal interlocking towers. Mr. Carpenter notes that nearly all of of the thousands of signal towers which existed in the United States have long since been abandoned, along with thousands of miles of track. Many official railroad records have been destroyed. Therefore, the drawings constitute a historic record of what was once an elaborate, complex and fascinating network of railroad tracks and signals.
Arrangement
Series I of the collection is organized by creator of the maps and alphabetically by railroad company thereafter, with the box list recording just the first and the last railroad in the box. The files within each box are organized by railroad reporting marks, which are letter abbreviations assigned to each railroad. Railroad reporting marks were devised so that the entire railroad name did not have to be recorded on railroad freight cars, or on paper or electronic records of car movements. The files also bear railroad code numbers, a one, two or three digit numbers assigned to each railroad for use on interline forms, where cars from different railroads were interchanged. Both the marks and code numbers were assigned by the Association of American Railroads, an industry service group to which railroads belong.
Series II of the papers consists of track charts and trackage rights charts, official station lists, signal track charts, interlocking diagrams and charts, and signal department prints for the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, Baltimore and Ohio Railroad, the New York Central System, Erie Railroad, Nickel Plate Road, Pennsylvania Railroad, Chesapeake & Ohio Railway (including major terminal maps), Central Rail of New Jersey, and the Delaware & Hudson Railway and other railroads in the Northeast and Midwest.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to New England railroads. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Acquisition Information
Boxes 1-12 of the papers were donated by Mr. Richard C. Carpenter in November 2010. Boxes 13-21 were donated by Mr. Carpenter in July 2011. Boxes 22 and 23, plus the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad track charts, revised December 31, 1967 (Item 24), were donated in January 2012. Box 25 was donated in November 2012.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Blueprints.; Maps.; Notebooks.; Notes.; Photocopies.; Photographs.; Railroads -- Indiana -- Maps.; Railroads -- Michigan -- Maps.; Railroads -- Midwest States -- Maps.; Railroads -- New England -- Maps.; Railroads -- New York -- Maps.; Railroads -- Ohio -- Maps.
- Series I: Hand drawn railroad track and signal maps, 1900-2001
  - Henry T. Wilhelm files
    - Arcade & Attica Railroad - Elgin, Joliet & Eastern (Box 1)
    - Erie Railroad - New York Central Railroad (Box 2)
    - New York, Chicago & St. Louis Railroad ( Nickel Plate) - Pennsylvania Railroad; includes photographs (Box 3)
    - Reading Railroad - Washington Terminal Company. Also includes articles, "mystery layouts," and record books of 860 drawings, done between 1919 and 1925, of interlockings of various railroad companies (Box 4)
  - William Bruce Coughlin files
    - Baltimore & Ohio Railroad - Indianapolis Union Railway (Box 5)
    - Lehigh & New England Railroad - Western Maryland Railroad; includes photographs (Box 6)
  - Richard C. Carpenter files
    - New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, 1896-1971
      - Drawings, notes, and lists pertaining to abandonments, signal stations, stations, divisions, and Boston area towers, 1960s-2000 (Box 22)
      - Maps, freight train schedules, timetables (employee and public), routing guide, Order of Railway Telegraphers Agreements, official lists of officers, Central New England Railway engine assignments (1924), list of signal tower numbers, 1896-1971 (Box 23)
      - Tracks charts, some created as early as 1926, revised to December 31, 1967, of the New Haven Railroad, New Haven District (western division of entire system), data includes track layout, bridges, crossings, stations, frog and switch references, curve data, alignment, and monumental center line station measurements, rail surfact, tie plates, line, ballast, jointed or welded rail, profile data. 98 pages measuring 25"x38", 1926-1967 (Item 24)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad subject files, organized alphabetically by city, A-L; includes signal rules, list of block stations and pay rates (1966), line lists by milepost, and a list of interlocking stations (Box 7)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad subject files, M-Z (Box 8)
    - Akron & Barberton Belt to Baltimore & Ohio Chicago Terminal (Box 9)
    - Boston & Maine Railroad to Chicago, South Shore & South Bend Railroad (Box 10)
    - Delaware & Hudson Railroad to Long Island Railroad (Box 11)
    - Maine Central to Wheeling & Lake Erie Railroad (Box 12)
- Series II: Official track and interlocking charts, 1889-1992
  - Baltimore and Ohio Railroad -- official station lists, operating and facility descriptions, roadway maps, track charts and trackage rights charts, 1889-1960 (Box 13)
  - New York Central System -- track maps and lists of stations and interlocking towers, 1942-1989 (Box 25)
    Scope and Content Note
    Information about contents of box supplied by the donor:
    The files primarily identified by the railroads which made up the New York Central System, including the Boston and Albany (B&A); Cleveland, Cincinnati, Chicago and St. Louis (CCC&St.L); Michigan Central (MC) (includes Canada Southern); Indiana Harbor Belt (IHB): New York Central (NYC): and Toledo and Ohio Central (T&OC).
    Some of these railroads have more than one file, each for an operating division or divisions. In the case of CCC&StL and NYC, there is a folder listed, by line, all the interlocking signal stations with their milepost locations.
    Details of some of the materials in the box:
    NYC New York to Chicago - Official railroad copy of a Track Diagram of Main Line Tracks, dated 1942. This is a strip map, neatly folded, showing the NYC tracks in solid lines and the tracks of other railroads in dashed lines, for the 962 miles from Grand Central Terminal, New York City to La Salle Street Station in Chicago. Stations, signal towers, track pans (for scooping water into the tenders of steam locomotives), yards and other operational facilities are shown.
    NYC Lines West Division Maps - List of Stations.This file includes NYCS Lines West - 1925 Division Maps; two copies, one marked up as indicated on cover and the other not marked up; and NYCS Lines West - Alphabetical list of Stations.
  - Erie Railroad -- official track and signal charts and signal department prints, 1912-1972 (Box 14)
  - Nickel Plate Road -- official station lists, physical data books, signal track charts, 1935-1964 (Box 15)
  - Pennsylvania Railroad -- official record of transportation lines, interlocking diagrams, track charts, system set of track charts, 1893-1960 (Box 16)
  - Track and interlocking charts for various railroads in Northeast and Midwest, A-M, 1890-1988 (Box 17)
  - Track and interlocking charts for railroads in the Columbus, Ohio, area, and various railroads in Northeast and Midwest, N-Z, 1919-1973 (Box 18)
  - Track and interlocking charts for various railroads in Northeast and Midwest, B-R, 1942-1985 (Box 19)
  - Baltimore and Ohio Railroad track charts (rolled), 1924-1961 (Box 20)
  - Oversized track chart books for the Chesapeake & Ohio Railway (including major terminal maps), Central Rail of New Jersey, and the Delaware & Hudson Railway, 1947-1970 (Box 21)